Guide to the McKim Mead and White Architectural Records circa 1875-1950 PR 42
New-York Historical Society
McKim, Mead and White architectural records
circa 1875-1950
New-York Historical Society
McKim, Mead & White
PR 42
286 Linear feet in 677 boxes and 13 drawers, plus 15 shelves of bound volumes and 3,046 rolls of architectural drawings
The McKim, Mead and White Architectural Collections consists of architectural drawings, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, financial records, and specifications documenting individual projects of the firm as well as its overall operations.
Scope and Contents
The McKim, Mead and White Architectural Record Collection spans the period from ca. 1875 to 1950 and includes the major portion of the firm's records. The collection consists of more than 61,000 architectural drawings, including ink on linen, blueprints, and other media; 1,500 photographs, including prints and glass and film negatives; 700 boxes of correspondence and specifications; 54 ledgers, including 17 bill books (1878-1947), 10 cash books (1894-1944), 8 contract books (1903-1930), and 9 journals (1882-1942); 30 photo albums and scrapbooks; and more than 300 original line drawings made to illustrate A Monograph of the Works of McKim, Mead and White, 1879-1915 (all numbers are approximate). The material contains extensive documentation of the firm's operations and of individual buildings, although most information about the firm's early years can be found in the photograph albums, clippings scrapbooks, and financial ledgers.
Included in the collection are Shingle Style, Colonial Revival, and other country houses in Newport, Rhode Island; urban residences such as the Villard Houses, New York; public commissions including Boston Public Library, Rhode Island State Capitol, and Prospect Park entrances, Brooklyn, New York; and universities, museums and libraries including the restoration of the University of Virginia rotunda, Columbia University and Pierpont Morgan Library, New York.
The collection is organized by the following formats: architectural drawings, correspondence, specifications, photographs, scrapbooks and photograph albums, newspaper and journal clippings, financial records, and publications.
More detailed finding aids for portions of the collection are available on-site. Researchers wishing to access the collection must schedule an appointment in advance. Requests for appointments and other questions should be submitted to the librarian for the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from Lawrence Grant White, Stanford White's son, in 1950, with additions from Mrs. James Kellum Smith in 1968.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment. Appointments must be scheduled in advance by contacting the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Most of the collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact printroom@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Biographical / Historical
Charles McKim (1847–1909), William Rutherford Mead (1846–1928), and Stanford White (1853–1906) established their partnership in New York City in 1879 and soon became the premier architectural firm in the United States. Between 1879 and 1912, the firm received nearly 1000 commissions, designing a wide array of residential, institutional, commercial, and public buildings in New York and other cities. Influenced by their extensive travels (and training) in Europe, the firm designed primarily in the Beaux Arts style, becoming the leading proponents of a return to classicism as an expression of American architectural character. The firm's work at the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago in 1893, featuring the "White City," also helped to launch the "City Beautiful" movement.
Among the firm's many notable buildings are Pennsylvania Station (1910, razed 1963), the Morgan Library and Museum (1903, expanded 1928), the Brooklyn Museum (1895), and the Municipal Building (1909-1915).
While associated primarily with the Gilded Age, the firm continued for more than three decades after the death of the last founding partner (Mead) in 1928, and trained many significant 20th century architects, including John Carrere and Thomas Hastings.
Arrangement
The collection is currently organized by format into the following eight series:
Series I: Architectural drawings
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Specifications
Series IV: Photographs
Series V: Scrapbooks and photograph albums
Series VI: Newspaper and journal clippings
Series VII: Financial records books
Series VIII: Publications
Related Collections at the New-York Historical Society
The personal papers of Stanford White are held by the Library's Department of Manuscripts.
Related Materials at Other Institutions
Additional McKim, Mead and White drawings and photographs are held by Columbia University's Avery Architectural and Fine Arts Library.
Charles Follen McKim's papers are held by the Library of Congress' manuscript division.
Architecture, Domestic -- United States.; Architecture -- United States -- 19th century -- Designs and plans.; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century -- Designs and plans.; Commercial buildings -- United States -- Designs and plans.; Country homes -- Rhode Island -- Newport.; Historic buildings -- United States -- Designs and plans.; Public buildings -- United States -- Design and plans.; Kendall, William Mitchell, 1856-1914; McKim, Charles Follen, 1847-1909; Mead, William Rutherford, 1846-1928; White, Stanford, 1853-1906
- Series I: Architectural Drawings
  - Subseries I.1: Rolled drawings
    Scope and Contents
    Included in this series are approximately 61,150 rolled drawings for over 1000 commissioned projects. Approximately 65 percent of these are tracings (mostly ink on linen), and 35 percent are print duplicates (mostly blueprints on paper). They consist of plans, elevations, sections, exterior and interior details, full size details, sketches, and shop drawings. Projects include educational institutions, banks, country estates, residences, clubs and casinos, hotels, memorials, government buildings, public buildings, commercial buildings, libraries, museums, churches, and hospitals in New York and elsewhere.
    The drawings were re-housed between 2009-2012 pursuant to a generous Save America's Treasures grant from the National Park Service, in partnership with the National Endowment for the Arts, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the Institute of Library and Museum Services, and the President's Committee on the Arts and Humanities.
    This subseries includes drawings of many of the firm's most important projects in New York City and elsewhere. An item-level inventory of the rolled drawings is available on-site.
    - 358 Fifth Ave., New York, NY, 1920 (Tube Various)
      Approximately 34 working and design drawings housed on 6 tubes.
    - 360 East 50th Street, New York, NY, 1924-1925 (Tube Various)
      11 design and working drawings on 3 tubes.
    - 1722 84th Street, New York, NY. Alteration, undated (Tube 1389.2)
      1 design drawing of plot plan on one tube.
    - 56th Street & Park Avenue, New York, NY (20 story apartment hotel), 1926 (Tube Various)
      50 shop and working drawings on 4 tubes. Includes, among others, plans of various floors.
    - 24 Gramercy Park, New York, NY. Alterations, 1936 (Tube 1739.2)
      23 working and design drawings, sketches, notes on 1 tube. Includes, among other, blueprints of various floor plans.
    - 269-271 Madison Ave, 1926 (Tube T0011.2)
      Elevations; floor plans; electric and steam plans
    - 227 Park Avenue, 1923-1925 (Tube Various)
      Interior and exterior details (multiple drawings all graphite on trace)
    - 277 Park Avenue-Small Scale Block Plans, 1924-1925 (Tube T1712.4)
      Six floor plans, all ink on linen
    - 358 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1920 (Tube T0861.2 & 4)
      mixed media drawings: column and beam details, framing plans
    - 360 East 50th Street, New York, NY - Apartment House, 1924-1925 (Tube Various)
      120+ mixed media drawings: plans, elevations, details and framing
    - 430 East 57th Street, New York, NY, 1925-1926 (Tube Various)
      80+ mixed media drawings: floor plans, utility details, apartment details, elevations
    - 60 Broadway, New York, NY, 1929 (Tube T1389.2)
      graphite on trace: height and setback overhead plan
    - 681 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY - Store and loft building - T's of Electric, 1912 (Tube T0813.4)
      ink on linen floor plans showing electric circuit work
    - 8 East 56th Street, New York, NY - alterations, 1927-1937 (Tube Various)
      70+ mixed media drawings: floor plans, surveys, details, schemes, layouts
    - 998 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY - Apartment house, Curtis Securities Company, 1910-1915 (Tube T1371.4)
      graphite on trace: framing plans, roof
    - Monograph Series, 1879-1915 (Tube Various)
      Monograph highlights McKim, Mead and White's most prestigious projects by publishing reproductions of ink on linen and ink on paper floor plans and elevation drawings; rolled drawing inventory lists these projects alphabetically and indicates the roll number(s) associated with the specific drawing reproduced in the publication
    - Abbott Academy, Andover, MA, 1913-1920 (Tube Various)
      5 drawings on 2 rolls; landscaping and gates
    - Adams, Henry (monument), Washington, DC, 1888 (Tube T1447.2 & .4)
      10 mixed media drawings; plans, elevations, sections
    - Adelphi College, Garden City, NY, 1928-1944 (Tube Various)
      90+ mixed media drawings; elevations, many interior and exterior details; Administration, Classroom, Garage, Recreation and Trinity College Buildings
    - Adirondack Power and Light Corp., Amsterdam, NY Power House, 1920-1922 (Tube Various)
      35+ mixed media drawings; sections, details, elevations, interiors
    - AIG Chemical Corp., Lefcourt Building, 43rd St. and Fifth Ave., NY, 1927-1938 (Tube T0859.2 & .4)
      25 mixed media drawings; interior and exterior details
    - Alexander & Watriss - Headstones, 1923-1938 (Tube T1712.4)
      Plans and inscription of tombstones
    - Allis, Mrs. Edward P. - Monument, Milwaukee, WI, 1894-1897 (Tube T0338.2)
      ink on linen plans, elevations and sections
    - Alteration of house for R.H. Williams Jr., Medham, NJ, 1919 (Tube T1111.2)
      graphite on trace; 5 over-sized details
    - American Academy in Rome - Memorial to C.F. McKim, and memorial to Founders, 1926-1927 (Tube various)
      mixed media, detail of inscription
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, New York, NY, 1925-1929 (Tube various)
      mixed media drawings, plans and inscriptions
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Washington Heights Educational Building, 633 West 155th Street, New York, NY, 1921-1922 (Tube various)
      175+ mixed media drawings, inquire within
    - American Battle Monuments Commission - War Memorial, Rome, Italy, 1928-1929 (Tube various)
      mixed media drawings: plans, elevations and sections
    - American Military Cemetery [Florence American Cemetery & Memorial] Assistant Superintendent's Quarters & Service Group, Florence, Italy, 1950-1953 (Tube various)
      50+ mixed media drawings: layouts, plot plans, sections, details, elevations
    - American Military Cemetery [Florence American Military Cemetery & Memorial] Bridge; Florence, Italy, 1950-1954 (Tube various)
      Separated Materials
      35 mixed media drawings: details, schemes,extensions, layouts, elevations
    - American Military Cemetery [Florence American Military Cemetery & Memorial] Entrance Gates; Florence, Italy, 1953-1955 (Tube various)
      mixed media drawings: plans, elevations, schemes
      - American Military Cemetery [Florence American Military Cemetery & Memorial] Memorial; Florence, Italy, 1947-1959 (Tube various)
        420 mixed media drawings: plans, elevations, inscriptions and sections
    - American Military Cemetery [Florence American Military Cemetery & Memorial] Reception Building; Florence, Italy, 1950-1951 (Tube various)
      10+mixed media drawings and correspondence; plans and elevations
    - American Military Cemetery [Florence American Military Cemetery & Memorial] Superintendent & Assistant Superintendent's Quarters; Florence, Italy, 1950-1951 (Tube various)
      3 drawings - plans, elevations, sections
    - American Military Cemetery [Florence American Military Cemetery & Memorial] Superintendent's Quarters & Garage; Florence, Italy, 1950-1951 (Tube various)
      50+ mixed media drawings: plans, elevations and sections
    - American Military Cemetery [Florence American Military Cemetery & Memorial], November 1949 (Tube T1264.2)
      New York Times Magazine - newspaper clipping
    - American University of Beirut, Lebanon, ca. 1950, many undated (Tube various)
      650+ mixed media drawings: Dining Hall; Physics and Engineering Buildings (framing); Faculty Apartments; Library; Hospital (preliminary and superseded) Electric, Heating and Ventilating; Hospital addition
    - Ames, F.L. Memorial, Unity Cemetery, exact location not indicated, undated (Tube T0471.2)
      ink on linen, 2 drawings: grave plot
    - Amherst College, Amherst, MA, ca. 1950s (Tube various)
      600+ mixed media drawings: Art Building/Gallery (proposed); Converse Library and Addition; Library Study Center Addition (proposed); Dormitoried (proposed); Dormitory alterations; Pratt Dormitory alterations; Walter S. Orr Rink; Appleton Cabinet alteration; Baseball Cage; Chemistry Building; Faculty Room Octagon; Gymnasium; Infirmary; Johnson Chapel; College Library (1916); Morgan Building; Power House; Pratt Feild Gates; Valentine Hall; Little Red School
    - American War Memorial, Rome, Italy, no date (Tube T1391.4)
      5 positive photostats: plot plans of grounds
    - Amsterdam Power House [Amsterdam, NY?], 1921 (Tube various)
      9 graphite on trace drawings: working and design
    - Andover Free Christian Church, Andover, MA, 1907-1908 (Tube various)
      25+ mixed media drawings: plans, elevations, details
    - 430 East 57th Street, New York, NY [Apartment House], 1925-1927 (Tube various)
      30 mixed media drawings: interior details
    - 277 Park Avenue, New York, NY [Apartment House] and railroad tracks below building, north from Grand Central Terminal, 1920-1924 (Tube various)
      325+ mixed media drawings: framing, plans, details
    - Arlington Memorial Bridge, Washington DC, 1925-1952 (Tube various)
      700+ mixed media drawings: Boundary Channel Bridge; Bridge Plaza and Water Gate; Cemetery Approach including Plaza; Cemetery Approach section 6; Cemetery Entrance - Contract section 7; Columbia Island Columns - Fluted Schemes and Section 3' Columbia Island Maps and Cemetery Sections; Columbia Island plans prior to June 19, 1934; Marine River 'God,' etc; Draw Span; drawings used for preliminary estimates included in tabulations dated November 28, 1933; Equestrian groups; drawings of J.O. Vegezzi; Equestrian pedestal; peliminary and final sketches of lamp posts; Lee Highway Bridge; Memorial entrance to cemetery (gates and fence); Seawall, Balustrade, sculpture, etc.; original working sketches for rendered drawings; Parkway approach and underpass; pedestal for Equestrian Groups
  - Subseries I.2: Flat drawings
    This subseries consists primarily of presentation drawings, but also includes other flattened architectural drawings and a few oversized photographs.
    - Madison Square Garden, plan of eighth floor above roof garden, 1894 (Box Flat files, Folder FF1)
    - Madison Square Garden, tower (vellum) (Box Flat files, Folder FF1)
    - Madison Square Garden, elevation of lower part of tower (Box Flat files, Folder FF1)
    - Madison Square Garden, section of tower up from first loggia (Box Flat files, Folder FF1)
    - New York University Library, section through reading room (Box Flat files, Folder FF2)
    - New York University Library, front elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF2)
    - House for Mrs. Patterson, Elevation on Burton Place (Box Flat files, Folder FF2)
    - Bank of Montreal interior photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF3)
    - New York Life Insurance Company photo (poor condition) (Box Flat files, Folder FF3)
    - Oakland City Hall competition presentation drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF4)
    - Boston Public Library (Box Flat files, Folder FF5)
    - Washington Arch, Washington Square Park, New York City (Box Flat files, Folder FF5)
    - Washington Arch, Washington Square Park, New York City, front elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF6)
    - Columbia University, drawings on trace (RESTRICTED: needs conservation) (Box Flat files, Folder FF7)
    - Madison Square Presbyterian Church, mounted drawing, front elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF8)
    - Madison Square Presbyterian Church drawing (Box Flat files, Folder FF8)
    - Hotel Nacional, Havana, Cuba. Charcoal on board, circa 1930 (Box Flat files, Folder FF9)
    - Metropolitan Museum mounted drawing by James Kellum Smitz (Box Flat files, Folder FF10)
    - Mounted color drawing of unidentified building (Box Flat files, Folder FF11)
    - Columbia University, aerial view (watercolor rendering, Jules Crow) (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, Unidentified university building, 1896 (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, Chemical Engineering Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, proposed Journalism Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, proposed art gallery, 1928 (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, layout of south field (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, East field, "Scheme A" (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, School of Natural Science, two plans on linen (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, Schermerhorn Hall, one plan on linen (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, south field, one plan on linen (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Topographic survey of a part of the grounds of the Bloomingdale Asylum (site of Columbia University), 1892 (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, pylons, 116th and Broadway (1 blueprint, 1 linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF13)
    - Columbia University, pylons on W. 116th St. (trace drawings) (Box Flat files, Folder FF13A)
    - New-York University (University Heights), half-side elevation of library dome, 1897 (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - Colony Club, front elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - University Club (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - Prospect Park, design for plaza entrance, drawing 2, 1894 (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - JP Morgan Library, detail of loggia (linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - J. P Morgan Library (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - Henry Villard residence (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - University Club (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - Brooklyn Institute of Arts & Sciences (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - New Bellevue Hospital, New York City (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - Columbia University, Philosophy Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - C.L. Tiffany house, NYC (Monograph series, plate 5A), 1884 (Box Flat files, Folder FF16)
    - Pennylvania Station, New York details of main waiting room, plate 310 (Monograph series), 1885 (Box Flat files, Folder FF16)
    - Washington Square Arch, north elevation (Monograph series, plate 40) (Box Flat files, Folder FF16)
    - Columbia University, Hamilton Hall, west elevation, college hall (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - Brooklyn Institute (linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - Taylor Residence (linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - Municipal Building (linen) (Monograph series) (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - Mount Royal Club, Montreal, Canada (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - H.A.C. Taylor house (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Knickerbocker Trust Co. (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - University Club (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Gorham Mfg. Co. (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Metropolitan Club (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Joseph Pulitzer house (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - New York Herald building (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - The Bowery Savings Bank (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Thomas Newbold residence (Box Flat files, Folder FF19)
    - Mrs. Clarence Mackay, Roslyn, NY (Box Flat files, Folder FF20)
    - St. George's School, Middletown, RI (Box Flat files, Folder FF21)
    - Columbia University, Low Library plaza photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF22)
    - Pennsylvania Station, New York at street level (Box Flat files, Folder FF23)
    - Municipal Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF24)
    - Madison Square Presbyterian Church, main doorway (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Arlington Memorial Bridge (Box Flat files, Folder FF25)
    - Harvard Union, Preliminary design living room (Jules Crow) (Box Flat files, Folder FF26)
    - Columbia University, Hamilton Hall, west elevation, college hall/Columbia (RESTRICTED: poor condition) (Box Flat files, Folder FF27)
    - Harvard University, memorial gate, Quincy Street (includes watercolor sketch) (Box Flat files, Folder FF28)
    - Amherst College Art Gallery (3 trace drawings) (Box Flat files, Folder FF29)
    - Proposed parish church, Roslyn, Long Island (Box Flat files, Folder FF30)
    - JP Morgan Library, trace drawing (Box Flat files, Folder FF31)
    - Trinity College, Hartford, CT, Field House & Connection to Trowbridge Memorial (Box Flat files, Folder FF32)
    - War memorial, Florence, Italy (Box Flat files, Folder FF32)
    - Maison de France, New York City (Box Flat files, Folder FF32)
    - Wharton School of Finance & Commerce, University of Pennsylvania, Bird's eye view (Box Flat files, Folder FF32)
    - 3 drawings of unidentified buildings (possibly the Municipal Building) (Box Flat files, Folder FF33)
    - 1 presentation plan of unidentified building (Box Flat files, Folder FF33)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station Improvement, Pittsburgh, PA, 14th St. exit (Box Flat files, Folder FF34)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station Improvement, Pittsburgh, PA, aerial view rain shed (Box Flat files, Folder FF34)
    - Unidentified church, section looking toward chancel (Box Flat files, Folder FF34)
    - New York Institute of the Blind, 5 different views of dormitory units (Box Flat files, Folder FF35)
    - American Academy of Arts & Letters, 1 mounted drawing of south elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF36)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City (plan at waiting room level, plan at street level, plan at concourse level) (Box Flat files, Folder FF37)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, Record Set of Reproductions (Box Flat files, Folder FF38)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF39)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF40)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF41)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF42)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF43)